<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-06-07T14:53:12-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Keton H. Kakkar</title><subtitle>Journalist; technologist; liberal artist and fairweather determinist. A sucker for good flora.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Normal People</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/books/2019/06/04/normal-people.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Normal People" /><published>2019-06-04T00:15:50-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-04T00:15:50-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/books/2019/06/04/normal-people</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/books/2019/06/04/normal-people.html">&lt;p&gt;I picked up Sally Rooney’s &lt;em&gt;Conversations With Friends&lt;/em&gt; in September 2017 after reading a review of it, probably in The New Yorker.
It was good; certainly. Quick, full of those quotidian thoughts one has but never develops. I read half then put it down. Syllabus week was over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday, N. and I stumbled into The Center for Fiction (recently transplanted to Brooklyn; once, the Mercantile Library). We got caught in a flash storm. &lt;em&gt;Normal People&lt;/em&gt;, the new Rooney novel, was on the shelf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reading what must have been the third extended feature on Sally Rooney (again, in The NYer) I was irked (and perhaps envious): what is special about this writing? It sounds like an email… it’s just regular writing! This was a few months back. Still, when I saw &lt;em&gt;Normal People&lt;/em&gt; finally on sale in America (Rooney is Irish), I bought it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out it’s not &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; writing. Unlike &lt;em&gt;Conversations,&lt;/em&gt; which, true to its title, focuses (in large part) on friends, this book’s on a couple, from high-school through college. Yet it’s not a book I could give to my younger sibling (it’s dark, and besides, though it’s present-tensed it’s texture is all retrospective; sibling has so much life yet to live!). It’s not one for the parents, either, though they generally like fiction, contemporary stuff included. “First Great Milennial Novelist,” “First True Novelist of the Internet Age,” these are some of Rooney’s recently-gotten laudatory monikers, exaggerated both by the granters and by me. Yet. For one it’s sparked in me a compulsion to blog, made clear to me that quotidian observations are worthwhile, that sometimes expansion is okay and not all writing needs to have been compressed and distilled before it is presented. For Rooney cares about the stuff of our daily lives in a manner both similar and not to the Victorians. It’s no surprise Normal People begins with an Eliot epigraph, or for that matter is called “Normal People.” Yet the narration is not totalizing like Eliot’s, nor its sentences as tightly wound. The narration is equally interpretive, perhaps, but it’s not snarky. I don’t even think it is judgemental. It is only in the last few lines that Normal People becomes overtly moralistic, with something close to direct value-laden intervention from a narrator. Not Eliot, then. A better analog among the Victorians might be Charles Reade, a prolific and contemporarily-famous, though now relatively obscure, novelist. Reade wrote novels for the sake of addressing social problems, and was unshy about ripping content from reality and stuffing it in his book. Rooney’s books have fabricated emails; Reade’s newspaper excerpts. The moralistic quality of Reade’s work (or at least in his novel &lt;em&gt;Hard Cash&lt;/em&gt;) comes not from the narrator, but from the plot; this seems closer, but still far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But ah. I don’t care about Victorian literature. I want to talk about Normal People. The book’s psychological portrait of a hetero-sexual couple in the digital age really got me. Depictions and descriptions felt uncannily similar. It’s a book that recognizes semi-universal truths about our age group of digital natives: assault, depression, the claustrophobia of space. The gap between Connell and Marianne is non-existent even as their individual identities are vividly distinct. They are constantly inside one-another (and we inside them) in a manner that seems simultaneously confining and liberating. This type of spacial malleability seems unique to being between the ages of 18-28 (and maybe younger) in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I picked up Sally Rooney’s Conversations With Friends in September 2017 after reading a review of it, probably in The New Yorker. It was good; certainly. Quick, full of those quotidian thoughts one has but never develops. I read half then put it down. Syllabus week was over.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Metaphysical Club</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/books/2019/06/04/the-metaphysical-club.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Metaphysical Club" /><published>2019-06-04T00:15:42-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-04T00:15:42-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/books/2019/06/04/the-metaphysical-club</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/books/2019/06/04/the-metaphysical-club.html"></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some Thoughts on Process</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/notes/2019/06/04/some-thoughts-on-process.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Thoughts on Process" /><published>2019-06-04T00:12:50-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-04T00:12:50-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/notes/2019/06/04/some-thoughts-on-process</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/notes/2019/06/04/some-thoughts-on-process.html">&lt;p&gt;I do not take easily to jotting thoughts, least of all for public consumption.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I do not take easily to jotting thoughts, least of all for public consumption.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2019/06/01/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2019-06-01T00:21:39-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-01T00:21:39-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2019/06/01/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2019/06/01/welcome-to-jekyll.html">&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add new posts, simply add a file in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory that follows the convention &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext&lt;/code&gt; and includes the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'Tom'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</summary></entry></feed>